<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | parker brody</title>
    <link>https://parkerbrody.github.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://parkerbrody.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://parkerbrody.github.io/img/icon.jpg</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://parkerbrody.github.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Exponence in Kiranti</title>
      <link>https://parkerbrody.github.io/project/3multiple-exponence/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://parkerbrody.github.io/project/3multiple-exponence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Inspired by an interest in the diachronic origins of uncommon typological structure, I conducted research into the historical development of multiple exponence &amp;ndash; the realization of the same grammatical information in multiple places within an inflected word &amp;ndash; among the Kiranti (Tibeto-Burman) language family. This repetition of inflectional material is a prima facie challenge for the notion that morphology is best analyzed as a one-to-one mapping between a segmentable piece of a word and the grammatical information it encodes, an assumption that is the hallmark of many theories of inflection. Instead, the attestation of multiple exponence in a not insignificant number of unrelated languages speaks to the strength of theories of morphology that view the association between morphosyntactic properties and their realizations as many-to-many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My research was built on the idea that uncommon morphology can be accounted for at the intersection of typology and ordinary diachronic processes of language change. I devised a comparative study of the Kiranti languages, a group of roughly 30 Tibeto-Burman languages spoken in Nepal and along the India-Nepal border. Kiranti provides a useful vehicle for examination of the diachronic development of multiple exponence, in that the family contains a major primary historical split which coincides with presence and absence of the feature in the modern languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comparative evidence from 17 Kiranti languages showed that redundant agreement inflection in periphrastic constructions, itself a typological feature of the family that is relatively uncommon cross-linguistically, serves as a prerequisite for multiple exponence. Moreover, I demonstrated the existence of cognacy between certain category markers in languages with multiple exponence and independent auxiliaries in languages without multiple exponence. Based on these findings, I argued that multiple exponence in these languages developed as the result of coalescence or univerbation of periphrastic forms in the Central and Eastern branches of the family. Interestingly,some Kiranti languages show evidence of multiple cycles of this process, resulting in modern synthetic forms with as many as four or more repetitions of the same inflectional material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While my findings are specific to the Kiranti group, future extension this line of research would involve investigating whether the analysis can be extended to additional languages and language families showing evidence of multiple exponence. Preliminary reading on multiple exponence in Ibibio (Niger-Congo) indicates the plausibility of a similar explanation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pama-Nyungan verb classes</title>
      <link>https://parkerbrody.github.io/project/1pama-nyungan/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://parkerbrody.github.io/project/1pama-nyungan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My current research project was born of my interest in the extension of modern computational methods to new areas of linguistic investigation. My dissertation provides an account of the evolution over time of verb conjugation classes in the Pama-Nyungan language family of Australia using Bayesian phylogenetic methods originally designed to model biological evolution. While the study of linguistic phylogenetics is relatively young, research has demonstrated the viability of the endeavor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of experimental design, I collected data about the verb conjugation classes of roughly 120 Pama-Nyungan languages, representing a sufficiently geographical and genealogical diverse sample of the family. Pama-Nyungan languages vary in terms of whether they contain or lack verb conjugation classes, how many classes they contain, and how verbs are divided into classes (i.e., based on valence or phonological properties of the stem). The properties of each given language give it a phylogenetic code or profile, which can then be used as input to Bayesian inference models in order to model the evolution of the verb conjugation class system within the context of the Pama-Nyungan family as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to answering this inquiry into the nature and development of a specific typological feature, my research speaks to broader questions about linguistic phylogenetic methods. These broader questions, in turn, form the basis for future extensions of my work beyond the dissertation itself. The first of these is a more comprehensive look at the utility of linguistic trait reconstruction to limit hypotheses of the structure of phylogenies themselves. It is important to note that due to the statistical nature of Bayesian inference, current approaches to building these phylogenies that stretch beyond the historical record are not limited to the inference of a single family tree. Instead, a distribution of possible trees is generated, with the probability of a given tree or sub-tree (representing a subfamily in common terms) given as the relative frequency of its representation in the sample. Bringing in new typological data that was not used in the original phylogenetic inference allows us to test the various hypotheses that exist within the tree sample, and further hone our ability to constrain the sample itself.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computational tools for low-resource languages</title>
      <link>https://parkerbrody.github.io/project/2segmentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://parkerbrody.github.io/project/2segmentation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A major component of my research interests is the application of modern computational tools for linguistic analysis to new domains of inquiry. This manifested itself in a recent research project, in which I investigated the viability of various stochastic and computational modeling techniques to aid in the documentation and description of low-resource languages, including finite-state representations of morphology and various approaches to supervised and unsupervised morphological segmentation of unsegmented text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stated goal of this research was to provide a tool for theoretical or field linguists who may only have access to limited amounts of data. Unlabeled inflectional paradigm data provides a challenge for automatic segmentation models, as the adjacence of specific stems and affixes often results in morphologically-conditioned phonological variation, meaning that the model will not see strong evidence for the existence of a low frequency phonological stem or affix variant. This is an issue not encountered in more traditional applications of these models to the task of segmenting words in a sentence or paragraph, as wordforms generally do not change their orthographic shape based on surrounding context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to demonstrate the viability of automatic segmentation models for aiding in small-scale linguistic analysis, I constructed a small dataset consisting of 320 inflected verb forms representing the full paradigms of five ambivalent verbs (can be both transitive or intransitive depending on context) in Bardi, an Indigenous language of Australia. The proposed computational model was employed in segmenting the Bardi dataset in supervised and unsupervised scenarios. For the supervised model, I also examined the utility of different approaches to creating hand-labeled training data, representing the initial effort of the linguist to hand-segment some of the inflected forms before automating the rest of the process. The findings of this work indicated that the potential for the application of modern computational tools in assisting with morphological analysis for low-resource languages is promising, as appreciable segmentation results were obtained from authentic, attested small-scale language data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of primary interest in extending this work is enhancing the representation of linguistic forms in the model to include information about the morphosyntactic properties they encode.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
